In personal finance, it's common for
people to focus on things that they
can't control, like trying to pick a
winning investment while ignoring the
things that they can control, like
setting the right goals and making a
solid long-term plan. This often leads
to mistakes. Some mistakes matter more
than others, and the biggest mistakes
can be the difference between living
paycheck to paycheck for life and having
a comfortable financial future. I'm Ben
Felix, chief investment officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to tell you about
the top 10 biggest mistakes in personal
finance so that you can avoid them.
This first mistake might be
controversial and I feel a little bad
saying it, but I don't think it gets
enough attention. Not earning enough
money. I know that's not completely in
your control. Luck, including the family
and the country that you're born into,
can have a big impact. Income inequality
is a complex issue, but it remains true
that for many people, especially younger
people, your human capital, your ability
to earn income by working or starting a
business, is your most valuable asset.
Investing in your human capital by
getting a formal education or learning a
trade, can increase the amount that you
expect to earn over the course of your
life, which is a pretty obvious benefit,
but it can also make your income more
resilient to bad economic times. More
education leads to more income on
average. And education in some fields
like engineering, healthcare, and
business have historically tended to be
more economically rewarding than others.
Maybe AI will change that. We will see.
I'm pretty happy having an engineering
degree regardless. Advanced
certifications like the CFA charter in
finance tend to boost average incomes
even further. More education does not
guarantee a higher income, but it
improves the distribution of income
levels that you can expect to
participate in. Income and education are
also associated with all kinds of other
important metrics like happiness at
least up to a point and both lifespan
and health span. Again, how much a given
person earns is a complex issue.
Education costs time and money. And that
aside, you shouldn't choose a career
that you dislike just because it pays
well. As always, personal finance is
personal. That being said, no amount of
frugality can solve the effects of
having a low income. Financial
well-being increases unsurprisingly
steadily with increasing household
income. Finding ways to save money is
important, too, and I'll talk more more
about that in a minute. But finding ways
to boost your earnings is one of the
best things that you can do for your
personal finances. The next big mistake
is not saving enough. If you've been
successful at boosting your income above
the minimum level needed to live, you
need to be saving a portion of those
earnings for the future when you may
want or need to stop working. In
addition to being necessary for things
like retirement, saving money is
strongly related to financial well-being
at all income levels. There's no perfect
amount to save, but there are some
guidelines. Someone with a very
aggressive savings goal, like early
retirement, might save a huge portion of
their income, while someone who plans to
work until a normal retirement age might
save less. Similarly, someone starting
to save later in life will need to save
more than someone starting early. A
common number that gets thrown around is
10% of your income in addition to your
contributions to government pension
plans like CPP in Canada or Social
Security in the US. It's probably
reasonable advice. An academic paper
finds that a 10% savings rate from age
25 to age 65 into a 100% stock portfolio
with 1/3 in domestic stocks and two/3s
in international stocks results in an
average retirement income level,
including social security above their
working year's income level. A 2011
study in the Journal of Financial
Planning uses historical data to
calculate the minimum savings rate you
would need to maintain in order to
retire, even the worst historical cases.
It's kind of like the 4% rule for
retirement spending, but flipped on its
head. The important point from that
research is that if you wanted to work
and save for 40 years and then live in
retirement for 40 years with a 70%
income replacement rate, excluding
Social Security in this analysis, you
need to save a minimum of 11.28% of your
income during your working years. If you
want to work fewer years, replace a
higher portion of your income, or have a
more conservative investment portfolio,
you'd need to save a higher percentage
of your income. I'll come back to that
point later. Figuring out the exact
amount you should be saving really
requires sitting down with a good
financial planning calculator or a
financial planner and mapping out your
long-term goals so that you can chart
the path to get there. It also requires
juggling priorities. For example, a
young family paying for daycare or
prioritizing family experiences might
settle to save less now and more later.
Speaking of goals, not setting financial
goals is another one of the biggest
mistakes in personal finance. People
make wild financial decisions when they
don't have at least a rough idea of
where they want to end up. It's worth
thinking hard about the financial goals
you want to set, which isn't always
easy. If I ask you what your financial
goals are, you probably won't be able to
tell me, even if you think you can. It's
weird to think about. When prompted
properly, people often realize that
their goals that they've set themselves
fall short of what they really care
about. There are a couple ways to elicit
more meaningful goals. One is using
categorical prompts, showing people
categories that financial goals might
fit into. Another is the use of a master
list, a comprehensive list of goals
collected from many people. In 2022, I
conducted a study where I asked 310
people to write down their goals. They
were then asked to double the list and
were then presented with the permavv
model of well-being as potential goal
categories. Perma V stands for positive
emotion, engagement, relationships,
meaning and accomplishment. And the V is
vitality. When you ask someone what
their goals are, they might say, "I want
to retire." But when you say goals might
fit into these six categories, they tend
to come up with more meaningful goals
that get closer to what really matters
to them. Using the data from my study,
Morning Star's behavioral research team,
this was pretty cool that they used our
data, found using natural language
processing that after being introduced
to the permavv model for the categorical
prompts, people tended to list deeper
goals that reflected their values rather
than the more surface level goals like I
want to retire. My study also resulted
in a master list of goals that people
can still find on the PW capital
website. This master list can be used in
addition to the permavv categorical
prompts as part of a structured goal
setting process. Understanding your true
goals is important because the path to
getting there to your true goals might
be very different from the path to
achieving some other surface level goal
or the uncharted path of doing whatever
feels right in the moment. Related to
setting the right goals and to saving,
another critical personal finance
mistake is overspending on the wrong
things. Spending money often feels good.
Having new material possessions feels
good, at least for a while. The problem
is that people adapt pretty quickly to
these feelings. Even something major
like a fancier new house will only tend
to make you happier for a bit. The
reason is pretty simple. Our happiness
is largely shaped by our
minute-to-minute experience rather than
our stable life circumstances which we
adapt to. The problem is that people are
not good at predicting what will make
them happy in the future. They tend to
imagine that things, often material
things, will boost their happiness much
more than they actually will. Think
about a potential major purchase like a
cottage or a boat. I'm not saying these
are bad purchases, but just just stick
with me for the example. When you think
about those purchases, you'll tend to
think about sunny days on the beach
where everyone's happy and getting
along, the boat's running, and the
cottage doesn't need repairs. Those days
do exist, but so does sitting in traffic
on a sweaty Friday afternoon trying to
get out of the city, kids fighting in
the back seat, the boat not running
properly or needing maintenance, and
having to rush to the cottage on a
weekday because of a burst pipe or
something like that. Again, I'm not
saying don't buy a cottage or a boat,
but I think it's important to consider
the time and money tradeoffs associated
with any major expense. How you spend
your time will affect your happiness
more than what you own. People who value
their time over money do tend to be
happier, make more frequent social
connections, and have a stronger
relationship with their spouse, and they
tend to be more satisfied with their
job. The other way this shows up in
financial decision-making is that all
else equal, spending less money today
gives you more ownership of your time in
the future. While we're required to
work, we trade our time for money by
necessity. Work has lots of
non-financial benefits, too. I'm not
anti work by any means, but being able
to choose how you spend your time and
choose the kind of work that you do is a
great position to be in. Spending less
today on stuff that doesn't make you
happy will get you there sooner, all
else equal. This highlights the
compounding long-term effects of
suboptimal spending today. For any
purchase or major expense, consider what
you are actually trying to accomplish by
spending those dollars and whether there
are more efficient uses of your time and
money to get there. Think about how
spending your money now will change how
you spend your time both now and in the
distant future. Related to the
compounding effects of poor spending
decisions today, another major personal
finance mistake is not taking enough
risk with your investments. Risk can
sound scary, but taking the right amount
of the right kinds of risk in investing
is one of the most important things that
you can do. Taking risk by owning stocks
rather than bonds or cash in a
diversified investment portfolio leads
to higher expected returns and has
historically led to higher realized
returns over long periods of time. The
expected returns available in financial
markets are there for the taking, but
they do require taking risk. What even
is risk? It's usually framed as
volatility. Volatility is certainly a
psychological risk, but for a long-term
investor who does not need to spend
their money tomorrow, I don't think
volatility is the best measure of risk.
I think a lot of people do get scared by
the concept, the the thought of risk
because they imagine losing all or a lot
of their money. And when markets are
volatile, it can seem like that's going
to happen. Or maybe they did lose all of
their money trying to pick winning
stocks or crypto tokens or whatever. But
total loss is an unlikely outcome for an
investor who owns a cross-section of all
of the publicly traded stocks in the
world through a lowcost index fund.
Stocks do not guarantee a good long-term
outcome. Don't get me wrong here.
They're still risky in the long run. But
the expected outcome from investing in
stocks is much better than that of bonds
or cash. The implied cost of not
investing in stocks is enormous. To put
it in terms of savings rates from one of
the papers that I mentioned earlier, to
match the expected retirement and estate
outcome of someone who saved 10% of
their income and invested in a 100%
globally diversified stock portfolio, if
you were instead investing in a target
date fund, which increases the
allocation to bonds fairly aggressively
over time, you would need to save 63%
more. 16% of your income. And if you
were investing in a 60% domestic stock
and 40% bond portfolio, you would need
to save 19% of your income, nearly twice
as much as the 100% globally diversified
stock investor. Where it gets really
crazy is looking at government bills.
Basically, if you're just holding a
highinterest savings account instead of
investing in stocks, you would need to
save 57% of your income to match the
expected outcome of the global stock
investors 10% savings rate. Getting
comfortable with taking risk is a good
thing, but it's easy to take the wrong
kinds of risk, which is another major
personal finance mistake. Trying to pick
individual stocks, looking for the next
Bitcoin before it moons, and using
options to bet on stock price movements
are more like gambling than investing.
I'd call anything that has a negative
expected return with the possibility of
some occasional wins due to luck
gambling. While investing has a positive
expected return with the possibility of
some bumps along the way. The difference
is that while you can win with gambling,
you can. It does happen. The longer you
play, the more likely you are to lose.
Just spend 10 minutes reading our Wall
Street Bets if you need proof. Whereas
with investing, the longer you play, the
more likely you are to come out ahead.
Investing is usually pretty boring. If
you already have a lowcost, diversified
portfolio, the next big challenge is not
getting distracted by all of the
financial products, advertisements, and
news headlines that can entice you to
make negative expected return bets. It's
possible to win while gambling, as I
mentioned before, leading you to believe
that you're really smart, but it's
important to remember what Daniel
Conorman said about expertise in
investing. It's very difficult to
imagine from the psychological analysis
of what expertise is that you can
develop true expertise in say predicting
the stock market. You cannot because the
world isn't sufficiently regular for
people to learn rules. If you do end up
on the winning side of a trade, you may
consider trading your luck on a negative
expected return gamble for positive
expected returns by investing in a
diversified portfolio. A British
Columbia man yoloed a Tesla options play
from $88,000 to $415 million before
losing everything.
Everything's obvious in hindsight, but a
little diversification would have gone a
long way here. The longer you stay in
the casino, the more likely you are to
lose. Missing tax planning opportunities
is another big mistake. Paying your fair
share of taxes is one thing, but there
are government approved tax planning
opportunities designed for people to
use. They're a rare free lunch. The
benefits of tax planning also depend
less on the uncertain future returns of
financial markets. Some examples are
income splitting with lower-income
family members either through strategic
household expense allocations or
prescribed rate loan planning,
optimizing the use of registered
investment accounts like the RRSP, TFSA,
and FHSA in Canada, donating appreciated
securities from a taxable investment
account rather than donating cash, and
maximizing the use of the primary
residence exemption for any period of
time that you owned multiple properties.
There are more examples for people with
corporations. Even simple things like
choosing the right tax year to use your
RRSP deduction can have a big impact.
Similar to and related to tax planning,
ignoring estate planning is another big
mistake. Not only can an improper estate
plan lead to tax inefficiency and estate
liquidity problems at death, it can lead
to added anguish for your surviving
loved ones. One of the biggest impacts
of creating an estate plan is ensuring
that your estate is set up to achieve
your objectives. without an estate plan
or at the extreme without a will in
place at all. There are prescribed rules
for how your estate will be distributed.
The problem is that those rules are
often at odds with what most people
would do given the choice. Well, with
the proper planning, everybody has that
choice while they are alive. Another big
mistake that can really hurt both
financially and psychologically is
marrying a financially incompatible
spouse. There are two broad spending
profiles, tight wads and spend thrifts.
Tight wads don't like to spend money
while spenthrifts do. The crazy thing is
that tight wads and spenthrifts are
statistically more likely to end up
marrying each other than another tight
wad or another spenthrift. Opposites
attract in this case. I guess the
problem is that the more spouses differ
on the spending dimension, the more they
tend to fight over money and the more
they report marital dissatisfaction.
Spouses with more similar spending
profiles tend to be happier. Financial
disagreements are already one of the
strongest predictors of divorce and
divorce can be financially devastating.
This is messy stuff. The tightwad
spendthrift trait is pretty stable over
time. So, if you're considering
committing to someone who has financial
tendencies that bother you, just know
that they probably won't change.
Underinsuring catastrophic risks is
another big personal finance mistake.
Insurance has a negative expected
return. It has to for insurance
companies to stay in business. Despite
its negative expected return, it does
make sense to buy insurance for risks
that if they materialized, you or your
family would not be able to recover
from. For example, when you have
financial dependence but are not
financially independent, it is very
important to replace your future
earnings in the event of an untimely
death with life insurance. Disability
insurance is important to ensure your
future earnings whether you have
dependence or not. Nobody likes to think
about death or disability, but not
planning properly for these unfortunate
events can be financially catastrophic.
covered calls. No, I'm just joking. FB
Canada, the credentiing body that issues
the CFP in Canada, defines six areas of
financial planning which at the very
least require conversations about these
common mistakes. Going through the
financial planning process with a
financial planner is highly likely to
reduce mistakes and improve expected
outcomes.